A Guide to the Wayne Perkins Collection, 1835-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Wayne Perkins Collection, 1835-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2010-078
2.6 cu. ft. 8 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Collection of records, memorabilia, and photographs relating to a number of North American railroads but concentrating mostly the Norfolk & Western Railway. Also includes papers of various Southwest Virginia families and a small set of personal papers.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Wayne Perkins Collection was purchased by Special Collections in 2009.
Biographical Note
Merrill Wayne Perkins, the son of Eli W. and Ethel Fielder Perkins, was born in Wythe County, Virginia in 1947. He married Elizabeth Williams and graduated with a degree in pharmacy from Virginia Commmonwealth University in 1971. He returned to Wythe County, working as a pharmacist in Wytheville. Among his personal activities, Perkins maintained memberships in the Wythe County Historical Society and the Train Collectors Association. Wayne Perkins died in Winston-Salem, North Carolina in 2004.
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials--mostly railroad-related--compiled by Wayne Perkins, a Wytheville, Virginia pharmacist and railroad enthusiast. The collection contains a wide array of materials--including business records, memorabilia and photographs--relating to a number of North American railroads. Significant among the materials are several items relating to early 19th-century railroads. The collection concentrates largely on the Norfolk & Western Railway, including ephemera produced by the company and materials produced by others about the company. The collection also includes assorted papers relating to various individuals and families (most from southwestern Virginia), apparently accumulated by Perkins in the course of collecting railroad materials. Also included are files relating to Perkins' involvement with various railroad enthusiast organizations, his model train hobby, and assorted personal papers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
Series I. Railroads and Associated Companies, 1835-1986. This series contains materials acquired by Perkins through his general interest in railroad history. The materials have no clear focus, though Norfolk & Western Railway materials comprise a large portion of the series. Included are a wide array of materials, including train passes, timetables, printed materials, business forms, legislative acts, train orders, company histories, ephemera and memorabilia. Of particular interest, perhaps, are an 1835 invitation to the opening of the Norwich and Worcester Railroad and an 1840 letter from the Bank Stock Railroad asking an unidentified minister to promote the railroad in his sermons. Also included in this series is a collection of dinner menus from several railroads, printed materials relating to the rail industry, and a set of souvenir buttons bearing railroad logos. This series is arranged alphabetically by business name, then by document type.
Series II. Individuals, Families and Businesses, 1881-1953. This series contains the papers of various people and companies apparently not directly connected to railroads but accumulated by Perkins in the course of pursuing his hobby. Included among the many disparate materials in the series are expense account records of F. W. Hawks, a cartographer working in Ohio. Also within the series are several pieces of correspondence between Robert L. Humphrey of Galax, Virginia and his sisters Mamie and Belle, together with some other Humphrey family-related papers. Also prevalent within the series are a number of bills of lading issued to G. W. Plumer, a Massachusetts merchant, and a set of telegrams between members of the Snidow-Dixon family in West Virginia and Southwest Virginia. A few freight bills issued to General G. C. Wharton may also be found in this series. Arranged alphabetically by surname.
Series III. Personal Papers, 1957-1996. Included in this small series are materials that relate to Perkins' personal life, though most of them are also connected to his hobbies. The series contains a folder relating to various railroad enthusiast organizations of which Perkins was a member and a folder relating to model railroading, including instructions, advertising matter, and other printed material. A very small selection of personal materials completes the collection and includes letters and ephemera, with some items relating to a George Wythe High School class of 1966 reunion. Arranged by subject matter.
Series IV. Photographs and Postcards, 1887-1987. This series contains images collected and created by Perkins and is devoted almost entirely to railroad-related subjects, including locomotives and other rolling stock; structures; and scenery. The series is divided into two subseries:
Subseries A. Photographs, 1887-1976. While a few of the images in this subseries seem to have been created by Perkins, and the creator of others is unknown, most of the photos are attributed to others. Included among these are significant collections from photographers C. W. Jernstrom and Harold K. Vollrath. As with the materials in Series I, the photos span subjects throughout North America, though there is a focus on the Norfolk & Western Railway. Included at the end of the photographs is a set of promotional photos for the Bendix-Feragen automobile frame-straightening system and a machine-pen autographed photo of Charles A. Lindbergh with his mother and the "Spirit of St. Louis." The railroad images are arranged by name of photographer, then by subject. Non-railroad images are grouped at the end of the subseries.
Subseries B. Postcards, [1906?]-1987. This subseries contains postcards collected by Perkins. While some have never been used, several of the older postcards include names and messages. Included at the end of the subseries are postcards depicting World War II-era combat aircraft and scenes from the southwestern United States. Railroad images are arranged alphabetically by company name, with non-railroad items grouped at the end of the subseries.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following books were removed from the collection to be cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
Burns, Robert E. and Stuart T. Saunders. The Inseparable Partnership: Education and Industry. New York: Newcomen Society, 1966.
Pettengill, Samuel Barrett. What Henry Ford Taught America. New York: America's Future, 1947.
The following map was removed from the collection and added to the Historical Maps Collection:
"Map of Roanoke County, Virginia, Compiled from Actual Surveys, Land Maps, and Data furnished by the Appalachian Electric Power Co., Virginia State Highway Dept., Norfolk & Western R.R., Virginian Railway" [C. B. Malcolm?], 1942.
Index Terms
Local Subjects:
Railroad
Contents List
- Series I. Railroads and Associated Companies, 1835-1986.
  - A Companies (Box-folder 1-1)
    - Amtrak rail travel privilege cards, 1982.
      [3 items]
    - Atlanta & West Point Railroad / The Western Railway of Alabama / Georgia Railroad travel pass, 1929.
    - Atlantic Coast Line Railroad
      - Passes, 1922-1961.
      - Timely Railroad Topics, 1927-1931.
        [8 items]
      - Map: "The Atlantic Coast Line of Railways to the South, n.d.
        [see Oversize Materials]
  - B Companies (Box-folder 1-2)
    - Baltimore & Ohio Railroad
      - Excursion to Washington D. C. broadside, 1891.
      - Pass, 1929.
      - System timetables, 1926.
      - Train orders 1967-1976.
    - Bank Stock Railroad letter to unidentified minister, 1840.
    - Boston and Albany Railroad eighth annual report, 1876.
  - Ca-Cg Companies (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Canadian National Railway passes, 1946-1965.
    - Carolina, Clinchfield and Ohio Railway pass, 1913.
    - Central Railroad of New Jersey
      - Pass, 1923.
      - Map and track elevation, 1927.
  - Ch-Cz Companies (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad
      - Pamphlet: "Letter of Thomas M. Munroe... and the Answer of E. Fontaine...," 1868.
      - Scrip book, 1921.
    - Chesapeake & Ohio Railway
      - Freight bills and receipts, 1886-1892.
      - Pass, 1929.
      - Passenger's check, 1929.
      - Car repair ticket, [1946?].
      - "Map of the Chesapeake & Ohio Railway and Connecticut," n.d.
    - Chesapeake and Western Railroad stock subscription contract, 1895.
    - Chesapeake Steamship Company pass, 1929.
    - Chicago Burlington & Quincy Railroad fire report, 1899.
    - Chicago Great Western Railway pass, 1952.
    - Cincinnati, New Orleans & Texas Pacific Railway correspondence regarding damage claim, 1886.
    - Cincinnati, Portsmouth & Virginia Railroad charges from Cincinnati Car Service Bureau, 1901.
  - D Companies (Box-folder 1-5)
    - Dickenson County Railway legislative act of incorporation, 1887.
    - Durham & Southern Railway statement of gross revenue accruing from tobacco products, 1951.
  - E Companies (Box-folder 1-6)
    - East Tennessee, Virginia and Georgia Railway freight damage claim documentation, 1886-1887.
    - Erie Lackawanna Railway / Delaware and Hudson Railway history news release, [1968?].
  - F-M Companies (Box-folder 1-7)
    - Florida East Coast Railway
      - Passenger's check, 1906.
      - Pass, 1922.
    - High Point, Thomasville & Denton Railroad history typescript essay, n.d.
    - Lake Erie & Pymatuning Railroad pass, 1961.
    - Long Island Railroad trainman's badge, n.d.
    - Louisville & Nashville Railroad Company pass, 1950.
    - Martinsburg, Scott's Corner and Beowawe Railroad lifetime pass, n.d.
    - Memphis & Charleston Railroad correspondence regarding freight damage claim, 1886.
  - Na-Nn Companies (Box-folder 1-8)
    - New York Central System conductor's check, n.d.
    - New York, Chicago & St. Louis Railroad ("Nickel Plate Road") typescript history news release, [1964?].
  - Norfolk & Southern Railway (Box-folder 1-9)
    - Bill of lading, 1907.
    - Letter from chief accountant to Alvah H. Martin, Jamestown Exposition Company, 1907.
  - Norfolk & Western Railroad (Box-folder 1-10)
    - Map: "Location of the Products of Fields, Forests and Mines Along the Lines of the Norfolk & Western Railroad and Shenandoah Valley Railroad," n.d.
    - Map: "Norfolk and Western Railroad and Connections," n.d.
  - Norfolk & Western Railway accident reports
    - Near Rural Retreat, Virginia, 1920.
    - Near Wytheville, Virginia, 1955.
  - Norfolk & Western Railway business forms, 1940-1978, n.d.
  - Norfolk & Western Railway memorabilia and ephemera, 1906-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)
    [2 folders]
    - Christmas greeting card from Passenger Accounting Department, 1906.
    - Oversized postcard, [1911].
    - "Service: freight handling efficiency" ribbon, 1921.
    - Invitation from Pocahontas Operators Association to cocktails at Greenbrier Hotel, 1956.
      [2 copies]
    - Ink blotter featuring image of N&W 600, n.d.
    - Greeting card images
      - N&W 613 in snow by John Terry, 1981.
      - N&W 2173 in snow by Fogg, n.d.
    - Locomotive photo identification cards
      - N&W 201, n.d.
      - N&W 600 n.d.
      - N&W 990, n.d.
      - N&W 1380, n.d.
      - N&W 2300, n.d.
    - Greeting card featuring photo by O. Winston Link: "Birmingham Special, Rural Retreat, Virginia," n.d.
    - "Injury-free service" stickers, n.d.
      [10 items]
    - Passenger ticket envelopes, n.d.
      [2 items]
    - Employee paper cap, n.d.
    - Order form for N&W mementos, n.d.
    - Matchbook covers, n.d.
      [16 items]
    - "Vanishing Vistas" photo card series
      - JT-567: N&W 609 east of Roanoke (1949 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-568: N&W 604, 1212, and 2147 (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-569: N&W 610 and passenger train on New River near Parrott, Virginia (1949 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-570: N&W 601 west of Roanoke (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-572: N&W 600, 1203, and 2123 (1945 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-574: N&W tavern-lounge-observation car on New River (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-576: N&W 602 on turntable (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-579: N&W 1597 (1966 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-580: N&W 2141 on New River (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-581: N&W 923 in Roanoke (1961 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-582: N&W 518 at Roanoke (1959 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-583: N&W 129 near Shawsville, Virginia (1942 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-584: N&W 128 on New River (ca. 1940 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-585: N&W 2123 (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-586: N&W 382 on South Branch of Holston River (1957 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-587: N&W 1209 near Vinton, Virginia (1940s photograph), 1972.
      - JT-589: N&W 889 west of Roanoke (1963 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-590: N&W Pocahontas passenger train near Singer, Virginia (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-591: N&W Pocahontas passenger train west of Roanoke, Virginia (1940s photograph), 1972.
      - JT-592: N&W 502 (1959 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-593: Tennessean passenger train with N&W 601 (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-595: N&W 610 near Vinton, Virginia (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-596: N&W 609 (undated photograph), 1972.
      - JT-598: N&W 606 and Powhatan Arrow passenger train (1949 photograph), 1972.
      - JT-599: N&W Powhatan Arrow passenger train at Pearisburg, Virginia (1952 photograph), 1972.
  - Norfolk & Western Railway printed materials. (Box-folder 1-15)
    - "Market Bulletin" (Norfolk & Western Railway Agricultural Department), 1920.
    - "'--For the Utmost Progress': a Story of Success and the Award of the Harriman Memorial Gold Medal to the Norfolk and Western Railway," 1926.
    - "N&W--Virginian Merger is Approved" (article from unidentified magazine), 1959.
    - "N&W Supplement to Midwest Railroader," [1959?].
    - Sheet music for "N&W Norfolk and Western Coal Train, Circa 1963-1964" by Jessie Baker, 1963.
    - "The Norfolk and Western and the Confederacy: Predecessors of N&W Rails in the Civil War," 1963.
    - "Along the Pocahontas Trail: Norfolk to Cincinnati via N&W," n.d.
    - McDowell-Wellman Serves Norfolk & Western Railway: World's Largest and Fastest Coal Shiploading Pier," n.d.
  - Norfolk & Western Railway Company stock certificates, 1964-1978. (Box-folder 1-16)
    [6 items]
  - Norfolk & Western Railway tickets and passes, 1891-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Norfolk & Western Railway train tickets, n.d. (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Norfolk & Western Railway timetables, 1936-1970. (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Norfolk & Western Veterans Association, 1929-1966, n.d. (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Norfolk Belt Line Railway act of incorporation, 1890. (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Norfolk Coal and Coke Company receipts, 1893. (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Norfolk Southern Railroad passes, 1929. (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Norfolk Southern Corporation promotional items, 1986, n.d. (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Northern Central Railway bill of lading, 1899. (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Norwich and Worcester Railroad invitation to opening ceremony, 1835. (Box-folder 2-6)
  - P-R Companies (Box-folder 2-7)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad
      - Pass, 1929.
      - "Vanishing Vistas" photo card JT-661: Pennsylvania Railroad 1361, 1972.
    - Philadelphia & Reading Railway pass, 1923.
    - Radford Little River Railroad Company act of incorporation, 1890.
    - Raleigh & Gaston Railroad freight bill, 1887.
    - Reed Island Iron Company freight charges on Norfolk & Western Railroad, 1886-1899.
    - Richmond & Danville Railroad
      - Freight bill, 1887.
      - "Map of the Richmond and Danville R.R. System and Connections," n.d.
    - Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railroad
      - Passes, 1923-1929.
      - Employee half rate order, 1970.
  - S Companies (Box-folder 2-8)
    - Seaboard Air Line Railway pass, 1928.
    - Severance & Weinfeld Ticket Brokers letter to S. R. Boyd of Cynthiana, Kentucky, 1902.
    - Southern Pacific
      - Pass, 1959.
      - Half-price ticket order, 1943.
      - Ticket envelope, n.d.
      - "Vanishing Vistas" photo card series
        - JT-20: Southern Pacific southbound "San Joaquin Daylight" near Lathrop, California (1940s photograph), n.d.
        - JT-137: Southern Pacific GS-5 4458 with train 99 at Santa Barbara, California (undated photograph), 1971.
        - JT-145: Southern Pacific train 99 north of Santa Barbara, California (undated photograph), 1971.
        - JT-180: Southern Pacific 4431 with train 52, "San Joaquin Daylight" (1955 photograph), 1971.
    - Southern Railway
      - Pass, 1929.
      - Special fare orders, 1951-1958, n.d.
      - Space reports, 1951.
      - Train orders, 1951-1976.
    - Strasburg Railroad brochure, n.d.
  - T-V Companies (Box-folder 2-9)
    - Turkey Gap Mine daily tipple reports, 1981-1982.
    - Virginia-Carolina Railway passes, 1912-1914.
    - Virginia, Tennessee and Georgia Air Line
      - Letter from W. T. Payne regarding claim, 1883.
      - Expense voucher, 1887.
    - Virginia Trailways bus schedule between Lynchburg, Virginia and Durham, North Carolina, n.d.
    - Virginian Railway
      - Passes, 1925-1929.
      - Freight tag, n.d.
      - Typescript history news release, n.d.
  - W-Z Companies (Box-folder 2-10)
    - Wabash Railroad
      - "The History of the Wabash Railroad," 1959.
        [photocopy]
      - Typescript history news release, n.d.
    - Western Maryland Railway train orders, 1973.
    - Winston-Salem Southbound Railway typescript history, n.d.
  - Railroad menus (Box-folder 2-11)
    - Central of Georgia Railway, n.d.
    - Chesapeake & Ohio Railway, 1941-1960, n.d.
    - Dixie Flagler, n.d.
    - Gulf, Mobile & Ohio Railroad, [1947], n.d.
    - Kansas City Southern Railway, 1941.
    - New York Central Railroad, [1941?].
    - Norfolk & Western Railway, n.d.
      [5 items]
    - Pennsylvania Railroad, n.d.
    - Pere Marquette Railway, n.d.
    - St. Louis-San Francisco Railway, n.d.
    - Wabash Railway, 1941.
  - Printed materials (Box-folder 2-12)
    - "All for One; One for All!" (Association of American Railroads n.d.
    - "Catalogue of Nathan & Dreyfus," 1882.
    - "The Hulson Locomotive Grate with Tuyere Type Grate Surface" (Hulson Grate Company Bulletin T-10), 1928.
    - "Memorandum of Agreement Between Railroads Named Herein and Their Shop Employes Governing Rates of Pay," 1916.
    - "Midwest Railroader," 1964.
    - "Pocket Guide to First Aid," 1961.
    - "Railroad Employees! Your Rights to Unemployment Insurance Under the Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act of 1938...," 1939.
    - "Rails and Rail Fittings" by John R. Zadra, [1951?].
    - "Saga of the Iron Horse" print series (Echelon Publishing)
      - "Chicago, Burlington & Quincy Class S4A 'Hudson,' 4-6-4," 1971.
      - "Great Northern Railway Class P-2, 4-8-2," 1971.
      - "Northern Pacific Class Z-6, type 4-6-6-4," 1970.
    - "Why--in the 1970's Do We Need Rail Passenger Service?" (National Association of Railroad Passengers), [1971?].
    - West Virginia bulk mail scheme, 1963. (Box-folder 2-13)
    - Sign requesting passengers to flush toilet after use, n.d.
      [reproduction]
  - Railroad logo souvenir buttons, n.d. (Box-folder 2-14)
    [23 items]
  - Unidentified railroads, 1887-1976, n.d. (Box-folder 2-15)
- Series II. Individuals, Families and Businesses, 1881-1953.
  - A-G (Box-folder 2-16)
    - Boaz, W. W. - receipts from Order of Railway Conductors, 1908-1909.
    - Charles R. Huddle Company stock certificate, n.d.
    - Cormany, J. A. - receipt issued by R. C. Grubb, 1909.
    - Davis, E. S. - receipt, 1888.
    - Fishburn, B. J. - bill of lading from Southern Express Company, 1903.
    - Furrow, R. V. - Railroad Retirement Board certificates of service months, 1938-1941.
    - Gilbert Bros. & Co. wholesale druggists (Baltimore, Maryland) shipping list, 1900.
  - Hawks, F. W. - expense records, 1906. (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Humphrey family papers, 1909-1934. (Box-folder 2-18)
  - I-O (Box-folder 2-19)
    - Keister, J. O. (Pulaski, Virginia) - letter fragment on druggist's letterhead, n.d.
    - Leonard, Frederick N. - telegram to A. P. Warrington, 1892.
    - Mahone, William - receipt issued to H. H. Hamilton for campaign expenses, 1889.
  - Perkins, Garrett R. - papers, 1908-1909. (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Plumer, G. W. - freight bills, 1884-1887. (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Snidow-Dixon family - telegrams (Box-folder 3-2)
  - T-Z (Box-folder 3-3)
    - Wharton, G. C. - freight bills 1881.
    - White, J. W. (Victoria, Virginia) - motor vehicle registration, 1929.
    - Yancey, R. D. - papers, 1884, n.d.
- Series III. Personal Papers, 1957-1996.
  - Railroad enthusiast organizations, 1957-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Model trains, 1934-1983, n.d. (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Personal papers, 1971-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
- Series IV. Photographs and Postcards, 1887-1987.
  - Subseries A. Photographs, 1887-1976.
    - Richard W. Biermann locomotive photos (Box-folder 4-1)
      - San Diego & Arizona Railroad 2, 1939.
      - Southern Pacific Railroad 1679, 1935.
      - Southern Pacific Railroad 2252, 1937.
    - E. Branagan locomotive photos (Box-folder 4-1)
      - New York Central Railroad Alco FA-1 1965.
    - C. W. Jernstrom locomotive photos (Box-folder 4-2-7)
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 2, 1958.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 12, 1957.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 56, n.d.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 105, 1954.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 108, 1938.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 111, 1939.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 114, 1948.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 116, 1954.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 124, 1958.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 125, 1948.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 126, 1953.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 128, 1951.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 129, 1947.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 130, 1947.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 133, 1954.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 134, 1947.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 136, 1956.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 137, 1953.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 137, 1959.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 207, n.d.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 232, 1958.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 279, 1957.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 376, 1935.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 477, 1959.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 557, 1947.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 563, 1939.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 600, 1941.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 600 (with 1203 and 2123), 1942.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 600, 1946.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 600 (with 2140), 1954.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 600, 1957.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 601, 1947.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 601, 1958.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 602, 1945.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 602, 1946.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 605, 1947.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 605, 1954.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 605, 1957.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 606, 1950.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 607, 1946.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 607, 1952.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 610, 1958.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 611, 1953.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 611, 1958.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 611, 1959.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 613, 1953.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 613, 1958.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 706, 1946.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 821, 1948.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 825, 1949.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 940, 1939.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 1131, 1952.
      - Norfolk & Western Railway 1137, 1940.